Hey everybody, welcome to this free
listening practice seminar. I hope
you're doing well.
So, I wanted to do a free seminar for
all of you so you can see how my
seminars are and see if you like them or
not. And if you do, then maybe you'll
consider becoming a listening time
member or a listening time super member
so that you can have access to more of
these types of seminars so that you can
improve your listening skills in
English. Okay? So, in case you don't
know,
I have a membership program
on our Patreon page,
patreon.com/listeningtime.
And if you become a member, it's only $2
per month and you have access to one new
listening practice seminar every month
and also an extra episode of the
Listening Time podcast. And if you
become a super member for $3 a month,
you have access to a new listening
practice seminar, an extra episode of
the Listening Time podcast, and one
other seminar that I've already
recorded, either a listening practice
seminar or a pronunciation practice
seminar.
But you have one additional one every
month if you're a super member. So, I
hope you enjoy this seminar and I hope
you'll consider becoming a member or a
super member if you like it so that
you'll have more of these seminars to
practice with. Okay, let's jump right
in. So, every seminar, every listening
practice seminar, we always want to
focus on the four essential elements of
English listening comprehension. Okay?
So, if you have trouble understanding
people when they're speaking even though
you know the words that they're saying,
like you can understand their speech if
you see it written down, but you can't
understand it if you hear it, uh this is
because
uh you're unable to understand
uh these four elements in their speech,
okay? These elements are stress,
reduced speech, linking, and phoneme
distinction. So, in every seminar we
practice with identifying different
patterns
um regarding these four elements, okay?
So, let me show you an example of each
one, all right? We're going to look at
this phrase right here, okay? I can only
wonder. So, first of all, let's talk
about stress. Stress refers to which
syllables and which words are said
longer and louder when we're talking. Uh
when we stress a syllable, this means
that we say it longer and we say it
louder than other syllables. If a
syllable is unstressed, then it can
become very short, very quiet, and its
pronunciation might change actually. So,
let's take a look at that in this
phrase. So, listen to it as I say it.
I can only wonder. I can only wonder.
Notice that there are a couple stressed
words here.
I'm going to say it one more time. I can
only wonder. Notice that the word only
is stressed, and notice that the word
wonder is stressed. I can only wonder. I
can only wonder. Okay, these are both
stressed in the sentence. However, this
word can, this modal right here, is
unstressed.
And so, because it's unstressed,
uh in this case, it uh it becomes
reduced speech.
Uh so, unstressed syllables often become
reduced speech. This means that they
become so short uh that their
pronunciation actually changes a little
bit, okay? So, you, uh as an English
learner, might say I can only wonder.
However, native speakers would not say
can. We would say can can. I can only.
Notice that it's not stressed, right? I
can only. We don't say I can only. So,
this word becomes reduced, and it kind
of sounds like this. I can
I can I can only wonder, okay? So, if
you're expecting to hear can, you're not
going to understand this phrase because
that's not how native speakers say it.
This word is reduced, okay? So, next,
let's look at linking. Linking is what
happens when a word ends with a
consonant sound, and the next word
starts with a vowel sound, okay? So,
what happens, we're going to see an
example right here. We have a word that
ends with a consonant sound, n
an n sound,
and the next word starts with a vowel
sound, only, o, right? So, what we see
here, uh with this linking, is that the
final consonant goes to the beginning of
the next word,
uh in the at the front of the next
vowel. So, instead of saying I can only,
we say I
can
only, okay? We connect this n
to the next vowel. Okay, instead of I
can only I can only I can only can only.
Okay, so this happens in English
almost every time that we have a final
consonant and a beginning vowel. All
right, so you might have trouble
understanding two words if they're
linked together like that. Lastly, let's
look at phoneme distinction. Phoneme
just means sound. Okay, so sometimes you
might misunderstand a native speaker
because you're expecting a different
sound because you don't actually know
which sound is in that word. You are
mistaken when it comes to the sound. So
this is a good example with this word
right here.
Wonder. Most of my students would say
this as wan wander, right? However, we
have another word in English, oops, that
sounds like that, wander. This is a
completely different word. Okay,
so that causes a lot of confusion of
course,
but the other problem is that when
you're listening, you might expect us to
say wander and when we say wonder, this
might be confusing because you're
expecting a different phoneme. You're
expecting ah, but in this case it's uh
wonder, right? Sometimes this letter o
becomes an uh sound. Okay,
all right, so we just saw examples of
these four essential elements. So now
we're going to take a look at our target
paragraph for today and we're going to
examine this paragraph
and look at these four elements
to see why it might be difficult for you
to understand the paragraph
Uh and to actually help you uh train
your listening so you can start to
identify these factors, these elements,
um so that little by little you can
start to improve your listening because
you can notice these patterns more and
you can expect uh to see these patterns.
So,
before I show you the target paragraph,
I'm just going to read it out loud. I
have it written down on my phone here.
So, I'm just going to read it. Now, I
want you to listen and I want you to see
uh how much you can understand if I read
it fast without you seeing it. Okay? You
ready? You couldn't have picked a worse
time to take a trip. We wanted you to be
here next week cuz it's your last chance
to see her this year. Okay, how was
that? Did you understand what I said?
I'm sure it probably wasn't easy to
understand uh
all the words that I said there, but
that's okay. That's why we're here.
We're going to take a look at this
paragraph together uh
and we'll see why it's a little
difficult for you. Okay? So, let me
scroll down here
and we'll take a look. So, this is what
I said. All right? You couldn't have
picked the worst time to take a trip. We
wanted you to be here next week cuz it's
your last chance to see her this year.
All right, we're going to take a look at
uh this paragraph and see these four
elements in the paragraph. So, we'll do
it word by word, phrase by phrase. So,
you couldn't have picked. You couldn't
have picked. Notice where the stress is.
You couldn't have picked. Couldn't have
picked. So, we have stress on this word
when we have a negative modal like
couldn't, can't, wouldn't, uh etc. These
are often stressed. And then our main
verb is almost always stressed or maybe
it is always stressed, right? So,
couldn't have picked. This word is
stressed and this word is stressed, all
right? But let's see what happens uh
with these two stressed words and this
word in the middle. So the way it sounds
like is kind of like this.
couldn't
da
picked, okay? So this have
right here, couldn't have, couldn't have
picked. This have, when it's an
auxiliary verb like this,
uh depending on the phrase, it can
become reduced often times to this, to
a word that kind of or a sound kind of
like the word of. So for example,
I should have, I would have, I could
have gone, right? It sounds like we're
saying should have, could have, would
have.
Actually, many native speakers think
that this is the real phrase, but in
reality it's should have, could have,
would have. But even native speakers
think many native speakers think that
the word is of because that's what it
sounds like when we say it at normal
speed. We don't say should have, would
have, could have, we say should have,
would have, could have, right? However,
if this phrase is followed by another
verb, right? If I have a word
afterwards, if it's not just the end of
a sentence, it can become even shorter.
And instead of of, it can become a.
couldn't have, shouldn't have, wouldn't
have, okay? So listen to this.
You shouldn't have gone, shouldn't have
gone, right? I'm saying you should not
have gone, but I would shorten it to
shouldn't have, okay? Shouldn't have
gone. If you've watched some of my other
seminars, you might have already seen
something similar to this because the
word of often becomes reduced to a,
right? A box of chocolates, right? A bag
of raisins, okay? So, because that
happens
and I showed you that could have sounds
like could of, then this of also becomes
reduced to a, okay? So, a really strange
pattern here, but this is really, really
common in English. You need to expect
this. Couldn't have picked, shouldn't
have gone, wouldn't have done, right?
So, you're going to hear these phrase
spoken very, very fast, okay?
All right. So, you couldn't have picked,
couldn't have picked. Notice that this
word is not pronounced picked or picket.
This ED just becomes a T sound, right?
Picked. Okay? So, there's no extra
syllable. There's no picket, it's
picked, picked, okay? The K the CK sound
is not aspirated. It's not k.
Right? It's not picked.
Right? We say picked, picked, okay? That
might be a little hard for your ears to
hear, but this is how these kind of
words are. Same thing with this, kicked,
kicked, okay? You shouldn't expect a
sound, right? You should just expect
kicked, icked, icked, like that, okay?
So, here we have an ending consonant
sound and then the next word is a vowel,
right? So, a. So, we're going to have
linking here. So, picked a. Picked a.
Right? You couldn't have picked a.
Okay? So, this T goes to the next vowel
sound. This word right here is always
pronounced a.
We never pronounce it as a, right? It's
a. So, in this case, the linking
makes it picked a, okay? So, you You
have picked the worst time to take a
trip. So, here worst, notice that the
pronunciation of o r is just like
whoops, it's just like this.
Er, er, we don't say warst or warst, we
say worst. All right, like we're saying
this word, were, were, worst. Okay? So,
you couldn't have picked the worst time.
Notice that the next word right here
has the same letter
at the beginning as the last letter in
the word before it. So, here we have an
ending t and then we have a beginning t.
So, when this happens in English,
usually these t's kind of blend
together. All right? So, instead of
saying worst time, we would say worst
time, worst time. It's like uh if I say
it uh like this, right? Worse
without the t and then the t in the next
one, right? Worst time. This is how we
would say that. Okay? We wouldn't go
worst time, right? When we end with a
consonant and the next word starts with
a consonant, we don't go uh
we don't let this air out, right? We
mute this letter. And in this case,
because it's the same sound, it just
blends together, right? Worst time.
Okay? So, many students uh they get
confused between this word and this word
because a lot of times they sound
similar to students when they're
listening because they don't understand
that maybe the next word is starts with
a t and it's just blending in and they
think we're saying this word. So, that
can cause some problems for sure. Okay?
So, you couldn't have picked the worst
time to take a trip. Uh if you've
watched other seminars, you also know
this by now, but the word to is always
reduced. We never pronounce this as to.
Okay? We always pronounce it as t d or
uh
depending on the context, depending on
the letter before it, okay? So, in this
case, timed uh right, the last sound
before it, mm, this is an m sound and we
have vibration with the sound. It's
called a voiced sound, mm. Because of
that, this t becomes reduced to
d, okay? So, another a similar one, if I
say had to, right? This d d d d
This has vibration, this d sound. So,
this is also reduced to d. I had d. I
had to go. I had to start, for example.
So, uh this word two is always reduced.
We never say two. Two is the number,
right? T O is p d uh. This is reduced
speech, okay? So, if we look at this
phrase, um you couldn't have picked a
worse time to take a trip. So, time,
take, trip. Those are all stressed
words, uh but the words in between them
are unstressed, okay? They're reduced.
Okay, and then we just have a little bit
of linking here because we have the word
take, which ends with a k sound, and
then the next word is a vowel. It's it's
the only one letter, it's just one
vowel. So, instead of take a, we would
say take a. Right? We don't say take a
trip, we say take a trip. Take a trip.
Right? When we say that fast, uh English
learners might think that it's like one
word or something, take a. Right?
They're not understanding that we're
linking uh the consonants with the
vowels, but that's what's happening
here.
All right, next sentence.
Uh we wanted you to be here next week.
So, uh Uh, let's look at this part here.
So, we wanted you to be here. So, notice
that uh the stress we wanted you we
wanted you to be here. Uh the stress is
on the word wanted and be, okay? Verb
verb, okay? These little pronouns here,
we, you, me, her, etc. These are usually
unstressed in our sentences, okay?
Uh when I talk to my students, usually
they stress every pronoun. They say you,
I, we. This is unnatural, okay? Native
speakers don't stress pronouns. These
are unstressed in our sentences. And so,
sometimes they can be reduced, and this
is one of those cases. When we have a
word that ends with D
and the next word is a pronoun starting
with Y, like you, your, yours, y'all,
etc., then we have a
uh an interesting pattern. So, instead
of saying wanted you, we say wanted
I'll put it like this. Wanted
you. We wanted you, okay? That's how we
say this. We wanted you to be here.
Native speakers do not say wanted you.
We say wanted you, okay? This
combination of the letter D with uh one
of these Y pronouns, you, your, yours,
etc.,
becomes this J sound, okay? So, for
example, if I say
uh I did your work, the way I would
actually say this is I did
your work. I did your. I don't say did
your, I I say did your. I wanted you, I
did your, I had you. We don't say had
you, we'd say I had you, right? So,
notice that pattern when you're
listening. You're going to hear it all
the time because when people are talking
to you, they often say you, yours, your,
you'll, etc. So, there will be many
times when the word before it ends with
a D and you'll hear this pattern, okay?
So, you need to expect that. We wanted
you to be here next week. So, here we
have another two. As we already saw,
this word becomes reduced. This is
reduced speech. So, in this case, wanted
you to same thing, we have a duh sound.
We wanted you to be here. duh duh Listen
to how fast that sounds. We wanted you
to be here. Wanted you. Wanted you to be
here. Wanted you to be here. So, the you
and the the this part, this word and
this word are pronounced very fast,
right? I wanted you to wanted you to
We wanted you to be here, okay?
So, this next part, well, this word is
stressed. Pretty easy to understand,
right? We wanted you to be here. This
word is also stressed. No problems
there.
We wanted you to be here next week. So,
in this this phrase here, next week,
notice that we have an ending consonant
and a
beginning consonant.
And this one is a T right here. So, the
T often becomes muted at the end of
words, okay? Just like with this
combination right here. Worst time, this
T was kind of muted or we could say that
it kind of blended together with the
other T.
In this case, it's kind of muted. So,
listen again. Next week. Next week. When
we say it fast, it just sounds like
this. Next week. Okay? It it's a little
bit too much for us to say st There
there It's too many consonant sounds. We
don't want to say next.
Right? So, as native speakers, we reduce
this and we say next week. Next time. We
don't say next time, we say next time,
right? Next Monday.
Again, we just mute the T. Next Monday,
all right? So, this muted T at the end
of words like that is really common,
especially if the next word starts with
a consonant, okay?
So, we want you to be here next week cuz
it's your last chance to see her this
year. So, the word because
I read it as cuz because this is usually
how we say the word if we're speaking
fast, all right? So, when I'm speaking
in my videos, in my podcast episodes,
I speak a little slower than how I would
normally speak. So, I often say because,
but this isn't how we would normally say
the word. We would normally pronounce it
as cuz, right? We just take off the
first syllable,
and the second syllable just sounds like
cuz. We don't say cause,
we we just say cuz, all right? And
sometimes it's even faster than that,
and it just sounds like cuz, just like a
C Z sound, cuz. So, this can be hard for
English learners to to hear when they're
listening. They're expecting to hear
this whole word because, and what they
hear is cuz, just like that. Cuz it's
cuz it's cuz it's your only chance, cuz
it's your last chance, right? So, you
want to expect this this word right here
to be reduced to cuz, okay?
Um all right, cuz it's your only sorry,
cuz it's your last chance.
Here we have this final z sound, this
voiced S sound, like a Z, and then we
have a beginning
a vowel right here. So, we have some
linking, so we would say cuz
all right, like this, cuz it's, right?
Cuz it's zits, cuz it's your last
chance, okay?
So, that's a little bit of linking right
there.
Cuz it's your last chance to see her
this year. Let's look at the stress. Cuz
it's your last chance. Cuz it's your
last chance. All right?
So,
in this case,
cuz it's your last chance, we have the
word last stressed, right? We have the
word chance, which is stressed. But
remember that this pronoun, right? These
pronouns that we have, you, your, his,
her, etc.
These are unstressed in our sentences,
okay?
So,
in this case, it becomes reduced speech.
Let's listen again. Cuz it's your last
chance. It's your It's your last chance.
Notice that we don't say it's your.
In this case, we say something kind of
like it's your. I'm going to write it
like this. It's your. It's your. Okay?
So, if I say,
"It's your only hope." The way I would
pronounce this is it's your only hope.
It's your only. It's your only. Okay?
So, this is just another case of this Y
kind of changing its pronunciation when
it gets reduced. We saw that with this
phrase, right? Wanted you. Right? The D
with the Y in front of a pronoun
is it makes it become a J sound. A T
with a Y makes it become a CH sound. For
example,
"I know that you're you're mad." We
would say, "I know that you're mad." The
T with the Y changes it to a CH. "I know
that you're mad." Okay? So, this Y in
these pronouns, you, your, yours, y'all,
etc.
This Y can often change its
pronunciation. This is another time. So,
it's your.
Uh again, if we have like this word
right here, that's your only hope. Same
thing. That's your That's your only
hope. All right? So, a word like that's
ending with t apostrophe s or it's
ending with t apostrophe s, uh this is
going to cause the Y to become an sh
sound, right? So, it's your, that's
your. Okay? So, I know this seems
strange and you're probably wondering
why.
That's just how English works, okay?
When we have reduced speech, letters
often times change their pronunciation
and I can't give you just an overall
rule. There is no overall rule. There
are little patterns that you have to
recognize and that's what I'm showing
you right here. So, it's difficult, but
you That's what we're practicing with,
right? You're going to see these
patterns and you're going to start to
notice them when you're listening, okay?
All right, let's look at the last part
here. It's your last chance. So, here,
last chance, we have an ending t sound
and it becomes muted. We don't say last
chance, we say last chance. So, it just
sounds like this, last chance with an s
sound at the end, no t. Right? It just
becomes muted, last chance. So, don't
expect to hear this last
All right? You're not going to hear this
sound, right? It's just last chance, the
last one. Okay? This word practically
always reduces to this word, okay? Even
though it's stressed in the sentence,
the t is reduced, okay? It's muted. So,
it's your last chance to see her this
year. In uh we have another two here,
but in this case the sound before it is
a voiceless sound a s
sound. There's no voice. So the two
becomes reduced to ta. Okay? So
in this case instead of saying chance to
chance ta. Okay? It's your last chance
to see her. Okay? It's your last chance
to see her. The stress chance to see
her. Right? Chance is stressed and see
is stressed. The two is reduced. Okay?
Last chance to see her this year. Okay.
And then we have this phrase right here.
See her. Okay? This H on pronouns like
him, his, her, hers, etc. This becomes
reduced
and we usually skip over this H
depending on the sound before it. Okay?
So in this case
see, right? This e is a vowel but it
ends with a y sound. Okay? So notice see
ya. My mouth is in position for a y. So
it really ends with a y a consonant
sound. Okay? So this is going to link to
the next word. It's going to skip over
the H sound and we're going to hear
we're going to say see
her see her. Okay?
The same thing if I say see him it would
be see him
see him. Okay? So the H on her, him,
his, hers is very weak. Okay? It's
usually skipped over. Right? The
consonant in the last word just skips
the H and it links directly to the er or
the im, okay? So in this case it's seer
instead of see her, seer this year. So
if you're not expecting that, this can
be very hard to identify when you're
listening. You're going to think we're
saying like this word for example, seer,
seer. Right? It sounds like what we're
saying, but really we're saying see her.
Right? Seer. Okay? So this is another
pattern that you're just going to have
to start to recognize and you're going
to hear it a lot if you really try to
recognize it, you'll notice it again and
again because every time someone says
her, him, hers, his,
any of these words,
chances are they're going to skip over
the H if there's a consonant sound
before it, okay?
So I want you to listen for that and
really try to notice that pattern.
Okay, lastly, the phrase this year,
okay? First of all, notice the stress.
We don't say this year, we say this
year. Last chance to see her this year.
So year stressed, this is unstressed,
okay? We don't say this year. That's
what many of my students would say, but
this is not natural, right? We want to
stress this noun right here, okay?
So there's one last thing you probably
noticed when I said this this phrase
here is we don't say this year, we say
this year, this year, this year. Did you
hear that?
Your last chance to see her this year,
this year. It's just like what we saw
here, right? It's her. So as I said,
this Y sound on pronouns is very weak
and it gets changed when it's reduced.
It can also happen with words other than
pronouns. So, in this case, it's just a
completely different word, year. It's
not you or yours
or you'll or any of those, but it also
happens here.
Um, so in this case, instead of this
year, it's this year. Okay? So, uh, you
want to look out for that. You want to
notice that when people are speaking.
Notice the Y sound, uh, changing,
especially if it's a pronoun like you or
or your. And notice that with the H on
pronouns, him, her, those words like
that. Start to notice those patterns,
okay?
All right. Well, we're done analyzing
our target paragraph. Hopefully that was
helpful for you. Hopefully this was, uh,
a good practice. And, uh, we do this in
each seminar. We look at a different
target paragraph and we analyze it, uh,
for those four essential elements, okay?
And so, if this was useful for you, if,
uh, you say, "Wow, no one's ever taught
me this before. I've never even thought
about this." Well, uh, I would, uh,
suggest that you become a Listening Time
member or Listening Time Super member
and because every month you have access
to these seminars, okay? I record a new
one each month and I also have a lot of
old ones that I already recorded that I
provide, uh, to Super members, okay? So,
hopefully this was helpful for you and
hopefully you decide to become a member
or a Super member. If you have any
questions, just send me an email, okay?
And I'm happy to help you out. So, go to
patreon.com/listeningtime
and sign up to become a member or Super
member today. All right. I'll see you
again next seminar.